"Does Increasing Protein Intake
Slow Age-Related Muscle Mass Loss?"
Population studies have found
that failing to meet
the recommended daily intake
of protein
is correlated
with a lower lean body mass,
and those exceeding the RDA
associated with significantly
greater lean body mass
compared to those failing
to meet the recommended intake.
Greater protein intake
has also been linked
to greater grip strength
over time,
though not considered enough
to be clinically meaningful.
You don't know
if these correlations
are even cause-and-effect
though,
until you put it to the test.
To see if increasing
the protein intake
for the elderly would help,
Harvard researchers
randomized older men
with moderately impaired
function
to controlled diets
offering the recommended
0.8 g/kg of body weight per day
or bumping them up
to 1.3g/kg a day
with a whey
and casein protein powder,
with or without
added testosterone.
Six months later,
there was no difference
in lean mass,
muscle strength,
fatigue, walking speed,
stair-climbing power,
or any of the other measures
of performance, function,
or well-being
with the added protein,
whether combined
with testosterone or not,
suggesting that the recommended
dietary allowance
of 0.8 grams of protein
per healthy kilogram
of body weight,
or about 50 grams a day,
is sufficient to maintain
lean body mass even in old age
and does not support
this thought
that adding extra protein
could promote bulking up
additional lean mass.
Even in studies that do show
an increase in lean mass
with protein supplementation
doesn't necessarily mean
an increase in muscle mass.
The field is said to be
"plagued" with researchers
referring to lean mass
as an indication of muscle mass,
but high protein intake alone
can cause significant liver
and kidney swelling;
and so, an increase
in total body lean mass
may just be a reflection of
"increased visceral organ size"
or water retention,
which also shows up
as lean mass.
For example, a 10-week
randomized controlled trial
found that elderly men
on twice the protein RDA
put on three pounds (1.35 kg)
of lean mass
over that of those
just getting the RDA,
but almost all the mass
was in their trunk.
When cross-sections
of their thigh muscles
were analyzed using CT scans,
there was
no significant difference
between the two protein levels.
Similarly, changes in
muscle area measured by CT
were found to be unrelated
to protein intake
in a prospective study
that followed
more than a thousand
older adults over five years.
The gold standard
for assessing muscle size
is the use of MRI scans.
Randomize hundreds of men
and women over 65 years old
to a year of a placebo control
containing table sugar,
versus a low-quality protein
(collagen),
versus whey protein,
with or without low or high
intensity resistance training,
and the exercise group
gained muscle,
but the protein
didn't help at all.
It made no difference
in muscle size,
strength, or performance.
Even the whey protein,
bumping them from average
protein levels up to 1.5 g/kg,
did no better than feeding them
the equivalent of sugar pills,
and the study was designed
and paid for by a whey company!
A two-year whey intervention,
one of the largest,
longest such studies ever run,
similarly failed to show
any benefits over placebo.
Put all these studies together
on using protein
or amino acid supplementation
to preserve muscle mass
and strength
in older men and women,
and overall, there was
no significant improvement
in lean body mass or upper
or lower body muscle strength.
That was without
concurrent exercise, though.
Maybe extra protein works
when combined
with strength training?
Very few studies
showed any benefit
to adding protein
or amino acid supplementation
during resistance exercise,
but enough trended
in the right direction
that if you put them
all together,
protein supplementation
combined with
resistance exercise
held a small edge
over resistance exercise alone
among older individuals.
After an average
of 18 weeks of training,
fat-free mass, handgrip,
knee extension,
and leg press strength
each increased
by an extra half pound (0.23 kg)
on protein,
though this did not translate
into any significant improvement
in muscle function
(such as rising from a chair,
stair climbing,
or walking speed).
Now here, "elderly"
was defined as "over 50."
Restricting the scope
to studies enrolling
actual elderly individuals
(average age 70 or older),
resistance exercise training
worked;
however, they found
no significant additive effects
to protein supplementation
on any outcome,
lean mass, muscle strength,
or functional abilities.
In non-frail older adults,
extra protein appears
to have little or no effect
on muscle mass, strength,
or performance
when taken alone
or added to an exercise regimen.
Okay, but what about
in those who really need it:
frail individuals?
One of the first things
doled out by doctors
is a quote-unquote
"nutrition shake,"
like Ensure®,
which are typically
ultra-processed sugary messes
of corn syrup, oil,
and protein concentrates,
often laced with
artificial colors,
flavors, and sweeteners.
Though Big Pharma giants,
like Abbot Laboratories
(makers of Ensure),
spend millions
of dollars a year
in lobbying
and campaign contributions
to help make these products
medicine's go-to choice,
but if you look at the evidence,
a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
on such drinks
for the management of frailty
found no discernable benefit
for any measured outcomes,
muscle mass, muscle strength,
muscle function,
frailty status,
cognitive function,
or mortality.
What about those suffering
from sarcopenia,
accelerated
age-related muscle loss?
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
concluded that protein
was a wash across the board
for improving muscle mass,
strength, or performance
among elderly
sarcopenic individuals.
The best studies on protein
or amino acid supplements
for unhealthy older adults
with acute
or chronic conditions
also found
no significant benefit.
Researchers have been trying
to find effective ways
to improve muscle mass
in older people for decades,
and so far,
only resistance exercise
has consistently yielded
benefits.
One of the largest
and most rigorous studies
to treat pre-frail
and frail adults
was published in 2021.
Hundreds were enrolled to test
the effects of leucine,
whey protein,
soy protein, creatine,
and a combination
of creatine and whey
versus a placebo control
(corn starch)
in the context of a 16-week
resistance training program.
The strength training itself
worked,
increasing muscle mass
and function,
but everything else flopped.
No added benefit to frail
or pre-frail individuals
taking any of those supplements
compared to taking
a corn starch placebo.
A similar trial of hundreds
of sarcopenic men and women
75 and older
given 40 grams
of whey-enriched protein a day
combined with exercise
for an entire year
with a 43-month follow-up
found that all the extra protein
did not slow
the deterioration
of muscle mass
and physical performance
significantly better
than a placebo,
all the more important
since it is one of the largest
and longest-lasting
randomized controlled trials
ever published on the subject.
Consumer Reports
noted that an investigation
of 134 top-selling
protein powder products
found virtually
all tested positive
for at least one heavy metal,
building on their own study
that concluded,
"You don't need
the extra protein
or the heavy metals
our tests found."